Walter Sutton Papers
Walter Sutton Papers
1958-1992
Sutton, Walter.
6 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, scholar, educator.Professor of English, Syracuse University, 1948-1985; born 1916. Collection includes correspondence, incoming and outgoing (1958-1992); book manuscripts. Notable correspondents include C.L. Barber, Stuart Gerry Brown, Lawrence Dembo, Byron Farwell, Robert Hudspeth, James Laughlin, Denise Levertov, Robert Emmet Long, Joyce Carol Oates, Tanure Ojaide, Roy Harvey Pearce, Robert Phillips, John Taggart, Brom Weber, Bette S. Weidman, Robert Weimann, and William Carlos Williams.
149500
Biographical History
Walter Sutton (1916-2006) was an American literary critic, editor, and teacher. He attended Heidelberg College, where he earned his B.A. (1937), and then received an M.A. (1928) and PhD (1946) from Ohio State University. He served in the U.S. Coast Guard from 1942 to 1945. He spent a year teaching at the University of Rochester then in 1946 accepted a teaching position in the English department at Syracuse University. He was made a full professor there in 1959, a position he held for nearly fifteen years, and was named distinguished professor of humanities in 1971. He also served as director of graduate studies (1968-1971) and as head of the English department (1971-1974).
In addition to his teaching career at Syracuse University, Sutton was a Visiting professor at University of Minnesota, University of Washington-Seattle, Princeton University, Colgate University, and University of Hawaii, and lectured at universities and meetings in England, Germany, the Netherlands, and Romania.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Walter Sutton Papers offer a detailed look at the work of an expert in the field of American literature of the Romantic period, modern critical theory, and in the works of Ezra Pound and William Carlos Williams in particular. The collection is divided into three series.
Correspondence-subject files reflect the wide scope of Sutton's scholarly and professional interests and his contacts with students and colleagues. Writings comprises manuscripts as well as correspondence relating to SUtton's publications in American literature and criticism. Memorabilia contains a dissertation by one of Sutton's advisees and several computer disks.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Writings and memorabilia are arranged alphabetically by type; writings are further arranged alphabetically by title.
Separated Material
An 1850 edition of Nathaniel Hawthorne's The Scarlet Letter has been transferred to Rare Books for separate cataloging.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Literature -- American Fiction; Barber, C. L. (Cesar Lombardi); Brown, Stuart Gerry, 1912-1991.; Dembo, L. S.; Farwell, Byron.; Hudspeth, Robert N.; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997.; Levertov, Denise, 1923-1997.; Long, Robert Emmet.; Oates, Joyce Carol, 1938-; Ojaide, Tanure, 1948-; Pearce, Roy Harvey.; Phillips, Robert S.; Sutton, Walter.; Taggart, John, 1942-; Weber, Brom, 1917-1998.; Weidman, Bette S.; Weimann, Robert.; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963.; American literature -- History and criticism.; American literature -- Study and teaching.; Authors, American.; Criticism -- Study and teaching.; Educators -- United States.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Walter Sutton, 1992.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Students, 1958-1992; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - A (Box 1)
  - Agenda (Box 1)
  - American Literature (Box 1)
  - Arms, Richard G., See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - B (Box 1)
  - Barber, C. L. (Box 1)
  - Basilius, Harold A., See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - Blackmur, Richard E., See Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays
  - Brown, Stuart Gerry (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
  - Carper, Thomas R., See Writings: Books: Plato to Alexander Pope
  - Chang, Pei Wen, 1985-1987; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Conyers, Claude, See Writings: Books: Modern American Criticism
  - Cookson, William, See Agenda
  - D (Box 1)
  - Daedalus (Box 1)
  - Dembo, Lawrence S. (Box 1)
  - E (Box 1)
  - Engels, John (Box 1)
  - F (Box 1)
  - Farwell, Byron (Box 1)
  - Ford Humanities Project
    See Princeton University Council of the Humanities
  - Foster, Richard, 1959-1962; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Furbush, Elisabeth (Box 1)
  - G (Box 1)
  - Gannon College (Box 1)
  - Goheen, Robert F.
  - H (Box 1)
  - Hamilton, Donald R.
  - Historical and Philosophical Society of Ohio, See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - Hudspeth, Robert N. (Box 1)
  - I (Box 1)
  - J (Box 1)
  - K (Box 1)
  - Kefauver, Weldon A., See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - L (Box 1)
  - Langsam, Walter E., See Writings: Books: Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays
  - Laughlin, James (Box 1)
    See also Writings: Books: Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays and Writings: Books: Plato to Alexander Pope
  - Laxson, Martha (Box 1)
  - Levertov, Denise (Box 1)
  - Levine, Edna S., See Writings: Books: Modern American Criticism
  - Literature and Psychology (Box 1)
  - Long, Robert Emmett (Box 1)
  - M (Box 1)
  - Mack, Maynard, See Writings: Books: Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays
  - Martin, Wallace (Box 1)
  - The Minnesota Review (Box 1)
  - Montella, Irene
    - 1975-1982 (Box 1)
    - Material relating to her dissertation on Maud Bodkin's journal, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Mussulman, Joseph (Box 1)
  - N (Box 1)
  - New Directions Publishing Corporation, See Writings: Books: American Free Verse
  - O (Box 1)
  - Oates, Joyce Carol (Box 1)
  - O'Connell, Paul E., See Writings: Books: Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays and Writings: Books: Modern American Criticism
  - Odyssey Press, Inc., See Writings: Books: Plato to Alexander Pope
  - Ohio Historical Society, See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - Ohio State University Press, See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - Ojaide, Tanure (Box 1)
  - P (Box 1)
  - Pearce, Roy Harvey (Box 1)
    See also Writings: Books: Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays and Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - Phillips, Robert (Box 1)
  - Pound, Dorothy (Box 1)
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc., See Writings: Books: Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays
  - Princeton University Council of the Humanities (Box 1)
  - Q (Box 2)
  - R (Box 2)
  - Rendall, Kenneth M. Jr., See Princeton University Council of the Humanities
  - Rinehart, Edith C., See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - Rodabaugh, James H., See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - S (Box 2)
  - Schlatter, Richard (Box 2)
    See also Writings: Books: Modern American Criticism
  - Shulman, Robert (Box 2)
  - Spectrum Books, See Writings: Books: Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays
  - Strauss, Ernest E., See Writings: Books: Plato to Alexander Pope
  - Syracuse University (Box 2)
  - T (Box 2)
  - Taggart, John (Box 2)
  - Thorp, Willard, See Princeton University Council of the Humanities
  - Tucker, Louis L., See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - Turner, Arlin, See American Literature
  - U (Box 2)
  - University of Washington (Box 2)
  - V (Box 2)
  - W (Box 2)
  - Walters, Everett, See Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
  - Watts, Harold H., See Writings: Books: Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays
  - Weber, Brom (Box 2)
  - Weidman, Bette S. (Box 2)
  - Williams, William Carlos (Box 2)
  - Wittke, Carl, See Writings: Books: Ezra Pound, A Collection of Critical Essays and Writings: Books: The Western Book Trade
- Writings
  - Books
    - American Free Verse: The Modern Revolution in Poetry
      - Contract (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1984 (Box 2)
      - Permissions, A-Z (Box 2)
      - Reviews (Box 2)
      - Royalty statements, 1973-1990 (Box 2)
    - American Literature: Tradition and Innovation
      - Contract (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1965-1982 (Box 2)
      - Promotional material (Box 2)
      - Royalty statements, 1969-1981 (Box 2)
    - American Poetry (1966)
      - Contract (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 2)
    - Ezra Pound: A Collection of Critical Essays
      - Adoptions (Box 2)
      - Contract (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Reviews (Box 2)
      - Royalty statements (Box 2)
    - Modern American Criticism
      - Manuscript, two drafts; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Manuscript, rejected pages from first draft, carbon copy; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Modern Criticism: Theory and Practice (1963)
      - Contract (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1959-1984 (Box 3)
      - Permissions, A-Z (Box 3)
      - Reviews (Box 3)
      - Royalty statements (Box 3)
    - Plato to Alexander Pope: Backgrounds of Modern Criticism (1955)
      - Contract (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
      - Royalty statements (Box 3)
    - Pound, Thayer, Watson and The Dial: A Story in Letters (1994)
      - Awards (Box 3)
      - Manuscript (Box 3)
      - Galley proofs, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Research files
        - "A.C. Barnes - S.T. 2 letters May 23, 25, 1923" (Box 3)
        - "D/S.T. New" (Box 3)
        - "J.S.W. to & from M. Moore 1921-1957" (Box 3)
        - "E.P. to Dial Worcester letters 1915-1920", 4 folders (Box 3)
        - "E.P. to Dial Worcester letters 1915-1920", 2 folders (Box 4)
        - "E.P. to W.L. 1) July ? 1920 2) 7/14/20 3) c. 1920" (Box 4)
        - "Letters S. Watson to S. Thayer 7/27/20 - 11/11/27" (Box 4)
        - "Letters to S. Watson 10/3/22-12/2/40 plus checklist of K.B. typescripts" (Box 4)
        - "S.T. to S. W. 3/18/20-8/11/25" (Box 4)
        - "S.W. to & from staff 1922-1928" (Box 4)
        - "W. Lewis to E.P. 6/30/46-9/24/46" (Box 4)
    - Stratford-Upon-Avon Studies (series title), See American Poetry
    - Twentieth Century Views (series title), See Ezra Pound, a collection of critical essays
    - The Western Book Trade
      - Correspondence, 1952-1979 (Box 4)
      - Manuscript (draft), 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Promotional material (Box 4)
      - Reviews (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Printed material
    - Hawthorne, Nathaniel The Scarlet Letter (Boston: Ticknor, Reed, and Fields), 1850; Transferred to Rare Books for separate cataloging.
  - Writings by others
    - Chang, Pei-Wen The Confucian Odes Made New: Ezra Pound's Translation of the Shi Jing (Box 4)
  - Miscellany
    - Computer disks, 27 5¼" diskettes (Box 4)